Okay
בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"א lamed aleph מנחות
Menachos thirty-one, we pick up at the bottom of ל' עמוד ב'
lamed amud bais הא איתמר עלה, ha-itmar alah, and actually I think
yesterday I got a little carried away and I said that the
case of רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri about a mixture of
old grain and new grain and taking מעשר maaser from it and
that the גמרא Gemara said that that was the case maybe that
was the case that עולא Ulla in the name of רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina said that we rule like רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon
Shezuri, and I got a little ahead of myself and I said
oh perfect so we now finally found a case. But actually we
did not find a case because as we'll pick up now הא
איתמר עלה ha-itmar alah so this is three lines from the bottom
of ל' עמוד ב', lamed amud bais, so yes that is a
case where רבי שמעון בן שזורי Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri says a
position but
nevertheless הא איתמר עלה אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן
ha-itmar alah ammar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani ammar Rabbi Yochanan הלכה כרבי
שמעון שזורי halachah k'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri that we rule like רבי שמעון
שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. ואי איתא ve-im issa and if it were
the case that עולא Ulla in the name of רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina when he said the הלכה halachah is like רבי שמעון שזורי
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and then he generalized it everywhere the הלכה halachah
is רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, but his first statement we
rule here like רבי שמעון בן שזורי, Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri, if
that was anchored in this case הוא נמי לימא hu nami leima
so he should also have voiced his opinion you know in reference
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's ruling. So the fact that עולא Ulla
said it without any conversation of any אמוראים Amoraim could not have
been dealing with this case of רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri
which already רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ruled like it and if עולא
Ulla meant to rule like it he would have chimed in his
voice with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan not have said it independently. So
we still do not have the core case which this statement of
עולא Ulla in the name of רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that we
rule like רבי שמעון בן שזורי Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri is anchored
because we have to find a ruling of רבי שמעון בן שזורי
Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri that no אמורא Amora has said anything about
it and therefore it would make sense that עולא Ulla said his
statement independently and not in conversation with any אמורא. Amora. So now
we are going to find two possibilities. אלא ella last line of
ל' עמוד ב' lamed amud bais אלא אמר רב פפא ella ammar
Rav Papa אשידה ashida it's talking about the case of a large
box. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak ammar איין
ayin it's talking about the case of wine. What are these two
cases?
אמר רב פפא Rav Papa ammar top of ל"א עמוד א' lamed
aleph amud aleph אשידה ashida we're dealing with the case of a
large box. דתנן detnan we taught in a משנה Mishnah in כלים
Keilim השידה hashida if you're dealing if you have a very large
box and the principle is that even though כלים keilim can be
מקבל טומאה mikabel tumah if you're dealing with a very large vessel
that can contain the volume of two כור kor dry measure
then it is you know considered more like the furniture as it
would be and not a vessel and therefore not מקבל טומאה. mikabel
tumah. All right so the שידה shida was an example like of
this it apparently was this very large storage bin used for storing
vessels
and how would you measure it to determine whether or not it
had could two כור kor could contain two כור kor of dry
measure. בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
very reasonable position נמדדת מבפנים nimdedes mipifnim you measure the inside volume
can it contain two כור kor that's the point whether it is
you know whether it has the volume to hold two כור. kor.
ובית הלל אומרים מבחוץ u-Beis Hillel omrim mibachutz בית הלל Beis Hillel
says no you measure it from the outside edge you imagine that
the thickness of the wall is also part of what this vessel
contains. So it is a leniency because the more we're able to
say it is of that size then the more we're able to
say it does not become טמא. tamei. All right so it's a
little unclear why we should do that but that's
בית הלל Beis Hillel's position. ומודים אלו ואלו שאין עובי הרגלים ועובי
הלזבזין נמדד u-modim eilu ve-eilu she-ein ovi haraglayim ve-ovi halavzivzin nimdad and
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai agree that you
do not measure the thickness even though you measure the thickness of
the wall and view that as volume being contained by this vessel
you do not measure the thickness of the legs you know the
legs don't define any contained volume they're just like little legs underneath
the box. And so you don't count the thickness of the wood
there towards the volume and you also don't count the thickness of
a type of a you know grate that goes around or crown
that goes around the top of the vessel. Okay so that's what
so that's reasonable that doesn't even that's not even the area of
you know what is contained by this by this vessel. רבי יוסי
אומר Rabbi Yosi ommer all right רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosi ommer
but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says מודים שעובי הרגלים ועובי הלזבזין נמדד
וביניהם אין נמדד. modim she-ovi haraglayim ve-ovi halavzivzin nimdad u-vineihem ein nimdad.
So this is a very strange position that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says no actually בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
both agree that the thickness is measured of the legs and of
the you know sort of the grate or the crown that might
go around. the metal work that goes around it, but the space
between them is not measured. Now, that you don't measure the space
between them, of course, makes enormous
sense. They're not holding a volume. They're just legs, you know, it's
just some type of a like of a filigree that's around the
top of the box. Okay, so obviously you don't measure that, but
it's very strange that רבי יוסי Reb Yossi claims that even בית
שמאי Beit Shammai would agree that you would measure the thickness of
the legs. That you measure the thickness of the legs towards the
volume and not the thickness of the walls themselves is quite strange,
but that is רבי יוסי's Reb Yossi position. Fine.
So this question is asked by the שיטה מקובצת. Shita Mekubetzet. He
has a different גרסא girsa of this משנה. Mishna. Anyway, that's strange,
but it's very reasonable that you're not going to count the space
between the legs. All right. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר, Reb Shimon Shezuri
omer, now here's our רבי שמעון שזורי, Reb Shimon Shezuri, אם היו
רגלים גבוהות טפח אין ביניהם נמדד ואם לאו ביניהם נמדד. im hayu
raglayim gevohot tefach ein beinehem nimdad ve-im lav beinehem nimdad. So
he's even more lenient. He says there are times you would even
count the space between the legs. When is that? If the legs
were within a טפח tefach of the ground, I mean they did
not hold the box more than a טפח tefach off the ground
or they held the box under a טפח tefach off the ground,
then it's like it's an extension of the box themselves. They're not
really significant in themselves, so you sort of see it as if
the walls of the box continue down through the legs and you
get to count all of the entire volume contained by the space
between the legs. That's a very big קולא, kula, presumably it would
only be according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Okay, but if it's
a טפח tefach high, the legs, then you don't count the space
between them. אין ביניהם נמדד ואם לאו ביניהם נמדד. ein beinehem nimdad
ve-im lav beinehem nimdad. So that would be the case where רבי
שמעון בן שזורי Reb Shimon ben Shezuri says a הלכה halacha and
it seems that no אמורא Amora says we rule like רבי שמעון
בן שזורי. Reb Shimon ben Shezuri. So that could be the case
of עולא אמר רבי יוחנן Ula amar Reb Yochanan that we rule
like רבי שמעון בן שזורי Reb Shimon ben Shezuri and why he's
not in conversation with any other אמורא Amora about that, because no
other אמורא Amora said anything about that ruling. רב נחמן בר יצחק
אמר אהיי, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar Ayay, רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says no, it says the case that it's
anchored in is the case of wine. דתנן, ditnan, we taught in
the משנה Mishna in טהרות. Taharos. רבי מאיר אומר שמן תחילה לעולם.
Reb Meir omer shemen techilla le-olam. Oil is always considered a ראשון
לטומאה. rishon le-tumah. What does this mean? The חז״ל's Chazal made, you
know, said that liquid, whatever something טמא tamei touches liquid, whether it's
an אב, av, whether it's a ראשון rishon one degree derived, a
שני sheni two degrees derived, anything that touches a liquid, the liquid
becomes a ראשון. rishon. Now, that is very strange. Normally, when you
touch something, טומאה tumah touches something, that thing gets one degree more,
you know, one degree lower, it's another, it's another level lower. So
if an אב, av, the father, the source of the טומאה tumah
touches something, that thing becomes a ראשון. rishon. If a ראשון rishon
touched something, it becomes a שני. sheni. A שני sheni touches something,
it becomes a שלישי, shelishi, if it's the type of thing that
can become a שני sheni and a שלישי. shelishi. But when it
comes to touching liquid, the הלכה halacha is that always becomes a
ראשון. rishon. So if an אב av touches a liquid, obviously ראשון,
rishon, but even if a ראשון rishon or a שני sheni touch
a liquid, it also becomes a ראשון. rishon. Now, what constitutes a
liquid? So רבי מאיר Reb Meir says שמן shemen oil always constitutes.
Now, what does he mean always? So תוספות Tosfos says nobody really
debates, רש״י Rashi isn't clear about this, but תוספות, Tosfos, we're going
to be discussing oil and honey and wine. And תוספות Tosfos proves
from other סוגיות sugyos that nobody debates that oil, honey, and wine
are considered liquids. What we're debating here is and what the משנה
Mishna said right before this is what happens when these things solidify.
You have oil that has hardened into a solid mass. Same with
honey. Same with wine. Do they still have a status of liquid
and would become a ראשון rishon regardless of what touches them? So
רבי מאיר Reb Meir says oil always, even if it's solidified, will
become a ראשון. rishon. It's still considered a liquid. וחכמים אומרים אף
הדבש, vachachamim omrim af hadvash, and the sages say same is true
with honey. Even when honey solidifies. Now, that's, you know, a little
strange because people like eat honey, you know, they don't exactly eat
oil. So honey you could imagine if it solidified, we would call
it a food. But he says no, even honey when it solidified,
even after it solidified is still considered a liquid and will still
become a ראשון rishon when טומאה tumah touches, any טומאה tumah touches
it. רבי שמעון שזורי אומר אף היין. Reb Shimon Shezuri omer af
hayayin. רבי שמעון שזורי Reb Shimon Shezuri says even wine when it's
solidified, becomes clumpy, that also is considered a liquid and that makes
sense because nobody eats wine, so even after it solidified it's considered
a liquid, still would be considered a liquid. So now the גמרא
Gemara just says מכלל דתנא קמא סבר יין לא? mikhlal de-Tanna Kamma
savar yayin lo? So when רבי שמעון בן שזורי Reb Shimon ben
Shezuri says even wine is considered a liquid, it sounds like the
earlier opinions would deny that solidified wine would be a liquid. And
how could that be? If solidified oil is a liquid, you know,
and solidified honey is a liquid, then certainly solidified wine, which is
the classic liquid when it's in liquid form, certainly that should be
considered a liquid. אלא, ela, so the גמרא... Gemara... גמרא Gemara
says, אימא Eima so rather say, רבי שמעון שזורי אומר יין. Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri omer yayin. רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says
no, not oil, not honey. When those are in liquid form, they're
a liquid, when they've solidified, they're a solid. Okay, for laws of
טומאה. tumah. Only wine, which is the paradigmatic liquid, only wine will
remain considered a liquid after it has solidified. Okay, so that is
to now we've ברוך השם Baruch Hashem have two possible cases
where רבי שמעון בן שזורי Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri gives a ruling,
one is regarding this שידה, sheda, this box and when it's not
טמא, tamei, the other is regarding wine and that only solidified wine
is considered a liquid, and these are two rulings of רבי שמעון
בן שזורי Rabbi Shimon ben Shezuri that no אמורא Amora voiced an
opinion about and therefore this is one or the other of these
is the case where עולא Ulla or רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said
here we rule like
רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, excuse me, רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi
Shimon Shezuri, not ben. That here we rule like רבי שמעון שזורי
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and that's why he was not in conversation with
any other אמורא. Amora. Very good.
Okay, תניא. Tanya. אמר רבי שמעון שזורי. Amar Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. So
now Rabbi Shimon, now that we're talking, one more case of רבי
שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri before we go on. אמר רבי שמעון
שזורי פעם אחת נתערב לי טבל בחולין ובאתי ושאלתי את רבי טרפון.
Amar Rabbi Shimon Shezuri Paam achat nisarev li tevel b'chullin u'vati v'shaalti
et Rabbi Tarfon. One time טבל, tevel, and רש"י Rashi clarifies that
we're talking here about טבל tevel of like really grain that was
חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות דאורייתא, trumos u'maasros de'oraisa, דאורייתא de'oraisa טבל
tevel that you did not take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from. And
that got mixed up with
חולין, chullin, with grain that has already been separated, had no obligation
of תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. And what are you supposed to do
here? Because it wasn't enough to affect
ביטול, bittul, for טבל tevel actually according, does not become בטל batel
because it's like a דבר שיש לו מתירין davar she'yesh lo mattirin
or whatever, other explanations. Anyway,
so it can't, it's not בטל. batel. So how are you going
to take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from the טבל tevel that's mixed
in? Oh, so what does he say? So he says: ובאתי ושאלתי
את רבי טרפון. Bati v'shaalti et Rabbi Tarfon. I came and I
asked רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. אמר לי Amar li and he said
to me: לך קח לך מן השוק, lech kach lecha min hashuk,
go buy some grain from the marketplace, meaning some flour, whatever, of
the same type, and this will be, you're buying it from the
marketplace, you're buying it from the עם הארץ, am haaretz, it'll be
דמאי. demai. דמאי Demai is rabbinically obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros
but not
דאורייתא. de'oraisa. ועשר עליו, V'asser alav, and take מעשר maaser from the
דמאי demai of the right proportions, include also the amount of תרומה
trumah if there's one of טבל, tevel, if there's one unit of
טבל tevel and one unit of דמאי demai that you just bought,
so take תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'maasros from two units of grain out
of the דמאי, demai, so it works also for the טבל. tevel.
Now why are these sort of considered to be like the same
type of obligation that taking from one can work for the other?
You normally need them to be the same year, you need them
to be equally obligated, you need them to be of the same
type of produce. So here though, one is דמאי demai and the
other is real טבל tevel that is mixed up with חולין. chullin.
It doesn't seem like they're the same thing. But here's the explanation.
So he says,
קסבר kasavar ועשר עליו. v'asser alav. קסבר Kasavar so רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon is of the opinion, דאורייתא ברובא בטיל. de'oraisa beruba batel. Even
though טבל tevel is not really בטל, batel, that's only rabbinically.
דאורייתא De'oraisa tevel is בטל. batel. So therefore
what you're dealing with in this mixture is something that מדרבנן m'derabbanan
is not בטל batel and therefore still חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות,
trumos u'maasros, but מדאורייתא m'de'oraisa is exempt. Okay, that's the grain that
got mixed up. And as far as the דמאי, demai, he also
holds: רוב עמי הארץ מעשרים. rov amei haaretz m'asrim. The majority of
עמי הארץ amei haaretz take תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, so דאורייתא de'oraisa
we can go by רוב, rov, the majority, and דאורייתא de'oraisa it's
exempt, but rabbinically it's obligated, הין hen והוה ליה כתורם מן הפטור
על הפטור. v'havei lei k'torem min hapatur al hapatur. And therefore they're
at the same level. At a דאורייתא de'oraisa level they're both exempt,
one because of ביטול, bittul, one because you go by רוב. rov.
And at a דרבנן derabbanan level they're both obligated, one is obligated
because we don't recognize ביטול bittul and the other is obligated because
we don't go by רוב rov and there's a principle, there's a
category of דמאי. demai. So therefore it's a דרבנן derabbanan taking on
a דרבנן, derabbanan, and they're exactly the same level. What I don't
fully get, I mean רש"י Rashi seems to address this a little
bit, is why you can't use the idea that we used yesterday
when you get two years of grain mixed up. Let's say you
have a mixture that is 10% טבל tevel and 90% חולין. chullin.
So you mix it up really, really well and you take one
unit of,
let's say 10 units for מעשר. maaser. Okay, let's say the entirety
of this mixture here is 10 units. It's one unit of טבל,
tevel, fine, I forgot what I said before, but one unit of
טבל tevel and 9 units of חולין, chullin, and it's all mixed
up well together, and now
you're
going to take... 10% of it, if you assume a total mixture,
10% of that unit is טבל tevel and 90% of that unit
is חולין. chulin. So you are saying the 10% of this unit
that I am taking that is טבל tevel should be effective, should
be מעשר maaser on the one unit of טבל tevel that is
mixed up into this mixture, right? It's sort of like, you know,
take, okay, it's a mixture, it's a mixture, you're taking on the
from the טבל tevel on the טבל tevel and the חולין chulin
on the חולין chulin doesn't mean anything. So I don't know why
you can't do that. רש״י Rashi seems to indicate that since the
חולין chulin is fully exempt, you know, it's not meaningful to say
I'm taking this unit as תרומות trumas and מעשרות maasros if only
10% of that unit is, you know, is obligated in תרומות trumas
and מעשרות maasros and the rest is total חולין. chulin. So we
can't take for some reason תרומות trumas and מעשרות maasros from within
the mixture; we have to find a different thing that the taking
from this other thing will work on the טבל tevel that's mixed
up and we have to get them at the same level. So
the answer was get דמאי. demai. Okay, that's that answer. So now
the גמרא Gemara says ולימא
ליה קח מן העובד כוכבים, v'leima lei kach min ha'oveid kochavim, why
not say buy grain from a non-Jew? Okay, non-Jew is we're assuming
דאורייתא de'oraita the grain of a non-Jew is exempt, דרבנן derabbanan obligated.
So again it works, obligation of a דרבנן derabbanan to a דרבנן
derabbanan and at the דאורייתא de'oraita level they're both exempt. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, קסבר אין קנין לעובד כוכבים בארץ ישראל להפקיע
מיד מעשר. kasavar ein kinyan l'oveid kochavim b'eretz yisrael l'hafkiya miyad maaser.
No, he's of the opinion that when a non-Jew owns land in
ישראל, Yisrael, it's still obligated in מעשר maaser דאורייתא, de'oraita, והוה ליה
מן החיוב על הפטור, v'havai lei min hachiyuv al hapatur, and therefore
grain bought from a non-Jew is חייב chayav דאורייתא de'oraita and that
won't work on this mixture of טבל tevel and חולין chulin which
is exempt דאורייתא de'oraita but חייב chayav דרבנן. derabbanan. איכא
דאמרי, ika d'amri, another version of this discussion, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so what what's his name, what רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said to
רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, he said to him קח מן
העובד כוכבים, kach min ha'oveid kochavim, he actually said buy from, get
from the non-Jew, and that the non-Jew is exempt דאורייתא, de'oraita, obligated
דרבנן, derabbanan, and exactly parallels your mixture of טבל tevel with the
חולין. chulin. קסבר יש קנין לעובד כוכבים בארץ ישראל להפקיע מיד מעשר.
kasavar yesh kinyan l'oveid kochavim b'eretz yisrael l'hafkiya miyad maaser. He holds
that a non-Jew does have ownership in ישראל Yisrael to change its
status and to exempt his grain from מעשר, maaser, והוה ליה מן
הפטור על הפטור. v'havai lei min hapatur al hapatur. So at a
דאורייתא de'oraita level the grain of the non-Jew is exempt and the
mixture of טבל tevel and חולין chulin is exempt because there's a
majority of חולין chulin and we would go by that and say
ביטול bittul occurred, and at a דרבנן derabbanan level they're both obligated,
so that's how one can work on the other. ולימא ליה קח
מן השוק, v'leima lei kach min hashuk, okay, why now so now
we're asking the same question in reverse, why'd he say buy from
a non-Jew, why not just say get some דמאי? demai? And then
again דמאי demai is exempt דאורייתא de'oraita and obligated דרבנן. derabbanan. קסבר
אין רוב עמי הארץ מעשרים, kasavar ein rov amei ha'aretz measrim, because
he actually holds that דמאי demai is not majority עמי הארץ, amei
ha'aretz, you would if you went by the דאורייתא de'oraita you'd say
it was okay. We cannot assume that the majority of עמי הארץ
amei ha'aretz take מעשר maaser and we actually have to assume that
it's like a fifty-fifty ספק, safek, and therefore when you buy דמאי
demai you are not exempt דאורייתא, de'oraita, you're obligated from a ספק
דאורייתא safek de'oraita perspective, and therefore the separation of דמאי demai does
not work on the mixture of טבל tevel and חולין chulin which
is full exempt דאורייתא. de'oraita. Okay, so that was one final interesting
discussion, you know, of with רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. All
right, now we are, oh, I keep on, I keep on wanting
this discussion to end before it's over. So last point, שלח ליה
רבי ירמיה בר שמואל לרב פפא, shelach lei Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Shmuel
l'Rav Pappa, רבי ירמיה בר שמואל Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Shmuel sent רב
פפא, Rav Pappa, הא דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר עולא אמר
רבי חנינא הלכה כרבי שמעון שזורי, ha d'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Ulla amar Rabbi Chanina halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, with that the
ruling that we've been dealing with, when he says here we rule
like רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri and we've identified that to
either be the case of the שידה shida or of the יין,
yayin, and then he went on to say ולא עוד אלא כל
מקום ששנה רבי שמעון שזורי הלכה כמותו, v'lo od ela kol makom
sheshana Rabbi Shimon Shezuri halacha k'moaso, and not only in this case
that he's ruling which we finally think we've identified, but then he
says everywhere רבי שמעון שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri says as הלכה halacha
we rule like him. So that statement that we always rule like
רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, אף בנתערב ליה טבל בחולין, af
b'nitarev lei tevel b'chulin, does that even apply to the case we
just discussed when טבל tevel gets mixed up with חולין chulin that
the way you solve it is you take different grain that's חייב
chayav דרבנן derabbanan and exempt דאורייתא de'oraita and then one works on
the other? אמר ליה אין, amar lei in, yes, he said everywhere,
yes, it applies to this case as well.
אמר רב אשי אמרי למר זוטרא, amar Rav Ashi amri l'Mar Zutra,
so רב אשי Rav Ashi says מר זוטרא Mar Zutra said to
me קשיא ביה רבי חנינא מסורא, kashia bei Rabbi Chanina mi-Sura, רבי
חנינא מסורא Rabbi Chanina mi-Sura was bothered by the fact that we
even questioned whether that statement would apply to this case of mixing
of of טבל tevel and חולין. chulin. פשיטא, Pshita, of course it
applies to this case. Top of ל"א ע"ב, Lamed-Alef Amud Bet, מי
קאמר במשנתנו, Mi ka'amar bemishnateinu, when עולא Ulla and the name of
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said we always rule like רבי שמעון שזורי,
Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, he didn't say we always rule like רבי שמעון
שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri in the משנה, Mishnah, כל מקום ששנה קאמר,
Kol makom sheshana ka'amar, he said we always rule like רבי שמעון
שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. So yes, we rule like him whether it's
a משנה, Mishnah, whether it's a ברייתא, Baraita, and we also rule
like him in this case which was not a משנה Mishnah but
a ברייתא Baraita of mixing טבל Tevel with חולין. Chulin. Okay, so
a lot of cases of רבי שמעון שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, a
lot having to do with תרומות Terumos and מעשרות Ma'asros and טומאה
Tuma and טהרה, Tahara, and we think we've identified the anchor case
for עולא Ulla אמר רבי חנינא amar Rabbi Chanina and we always
rule like רבי שמעון שזורי. Rabbi Shimon Shezuri. Now, whew, back to
discussing a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Second line from the top ל"א
ע"ב. Lamed-Alef Amud Bet. אמר רב זעירא אמר רב חננאל אמר רב,
Amar Rav Zeira amar Rav Chananel amar Rav, so רב זעירא Rav
Zeira in the name of רב חננאל Rav Chananel said in the
name of רב, Rav, קרע הבא בשתי שיטים יתפור. Kera haba bishtei
shitin yitpor. If you have a tear in the קלף klaf of
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and the tear, it's a vertical tear
and it breaks through two lines of text, through two lines of
text, you can sew it up. Now, if it's going to break
through, it theoretically could break through and not touch any letter, but
if it does break through and break a letter in those two
lines, then you would have to rewrite that letter because you cannot
create a letter through sewing two pieces of paper together. That would
be a case of like חק תוכות Chak tochot or whatever. You
do something else and the letter gets made. You have to actually
write the letter on the קלף. klaf. But fine, you sew up
the קלף klaf and then you fix the letter, but the קלף
klaf is still כשר kosher even though it cuts through two lines.
בשלוש לא יתפור. Bishalosh lo yitpor.
However, if it cuts through three lines, then you can't sew it
up. Okay, then that's too like it makes the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah look like patchwork and look ugly and therefore you got to
basically replace the whole קלף klaf which is a pretty big demand.
Okay, אמר ליה רב זוטרא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Zutra le-Rav
Ashi, רב זוטרא Rav Zutra said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, הכי
אמר רב ירמיה מדיפתי, Hachi amar Rav Yirmeya mi-Difti, this is what
רב ירמיה Rav Yirmeya of דיפתי Difti said, משמיה דרבא, mishmeih de-Rava,
in the name of רבא, Rava, הא דאמרן בשלוש לא יתפור לא
אמרן אלא בעתיקתא. Ha de-amran bishalosh lo yitpor lo amran ela be-atikta.
That which we say that by three it makes it look ugly
and patchwork and you can't sew it up, that's only by like
an old ספר. Sefer. So the קלף klaf is old and it's
being all sewn up, so that really gets to a point of
being unseemly. אבל בחדתא לית לן בה, Aval be-chadta leit lan bah,
and if it's a new ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, alright, so you
have one place where you did some significant stitching.
ולא עתיקתא עתיקתא ממש ולא חדתא חדתא ממש, Velo atikta atikta mamash
velo chadta chadta mamash,
and old doesn't literally mean old and new doesn't literally mean new,
אלא הא דאפיצן הא דלא אפיצן. ela ha de-afitzan ha de-lo afitzan.
Old means when and new means that it has not been treated
with gall and which was a way they would treat their קלף,
klaf, and old means it has been treated with like gall nut.
And what that would do is that that would make the give
the קלף klaf a black and a dark look, they would do
it presumably so that the writing you could not it would stay
and you would sort of see if you would try to scrape
it off. So there there were reasons that they would do it,
but it would give the קלף klaf an older look. And therefore
if it has that older look, then that's when cutting through three
lines is a problem. If it looks newer even if it technically
is old,
then even three lines would not be bad, would not be a
problem. Okay, מהני מילי בגידין. Mahani mili be-gidin. Now, what are we
talking about when you can sew up a tear? That's if you
use
catgut, like thread made from intestine.
אבל בגרדין, Aval be-gardin, if you're using normal thread, לא, lo, you
can't do it. Now, some say you can't do it because there's
a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Mi-Sinai that you need to
use catgut, you need to use thread made from intestine for the
sewing of the קלפים. klafim. Others say no, that הלכה למשה מסיני
Halacha Lemoshe Mi-Sinai is only about the sewing of the קלפים klafim
to one another. This type
of a fix that you're doing, of a sewing together of a
tear,
that's not a הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Lemoshe Mi-Sinai of needing catgut,
but the problem here is just aesthetics. And if you use a
type of a thread, it'll stand out too much against the background
of the קלף, klaf, it won't be as transparent, and that's why
it'll be problematic. Okay, בעי רב יהודה בר אבא, Ba'ei Rav Yehuda
bar Abba, רב יהודה בר אבא Rav Yehuda bar Abba asked, בין
דף לדף. Bein daf le-daf. Let's say the tear goes three lines
down but it doesn't cut into the line, it just cuts the
space between the columns, so it's only cutting air space as it
were. בין שיטה לשיטה, Bein shita le-shita, or it was a horizontal
tear and it tore between two lines, מאי, mai,
what's the הלכה? halacha? Do can you sew that up regardless of
how long because it's it doesn't it's not as disfiguring as it
would be, or no, even there it would be
a problem? Now we're going to get to a מזוזה. Mezuza. If
you write a מזוזה Mezuza that it's only two words per line,
so like a very long and narrow text. That's how Rashi reads
שתים שתים. Shtayim shtayim. It's going to be כשרה. Keshera. Okay. איבעיא
להו. Ibay'o lehu. Now they asked the question: שתים ושלש ואחת מהו?
Shtayim veshalosh ve'achat mahu? Let's say you wrote it and if you
look in the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet there are very nice visual
examples. Let's say you wrote it: two words on one line, three
words on the next, one word on the next. והיו הדברים Vehayu
hadevarim on the first line, האלה אשר אנכי Ha'eileh asher anochi the
second line, מצוך Metzavecha on the third line. Okay. What's the story?
Now you might think, you know, doesn't this all have to be
like right and left justified? So what exactly is the story here?
Now part of the reason we're asking by the מזוזה Mezuza text
is if you remember like a ספר תורה Sefer Torah you can't
have columns that are too small, you know, and so on but
here it's like one or two
paragraphs so maybe it doesn't exactly follow those parameters. Maybe it doesn't
require, you know, right and left justified. So what's the story? So
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, כל שכן
שעשאה כשירה. Kol shekein she'as'ah keshira. And the answer is particularly shocking.
That's even better! Of course that's fine. Now it looks like the
שירה, Shira, you know, it looks like the way you write the
poems or the songs in the תורה, Torah, particularly like the song
of אז ישיר Az Yashir which the גמרא Gemara describes as אריח
על גבי לבינה. Ariach al gabei leveinah. You know, it's sort of
like staggered. Like you have, you know, like if you imagine there
are three spaces in each line, the top like we'll call them
one, two, and three. The first line has the text on two
and the bottom line has the text on one and three. You
know, but the two sort of like overlaps the one and the
two. So and then you sort of repeat that type of
staggering. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that that's a normal way of
writing a poem and that's a very appropriate. Again, I don't know
why it's appropriate. Shouldn't this look more like a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah rather than a poem? So the—רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot do
not explain this. But that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So of
course that's okay.
מיתיבי. Meiteivei. Now they ask you on this: עשאה כשירה או שירה
כמותה—we As'ah keshira o shira kemotah have a teaching that if you
made it, we'll see what the it is in a minute, like
the שירה, Shira, a part of the text that's supposed to be
normal columned and you made it staggered like the שירה, Shira, or
you made the שירה—like Shira the שירת הים Shirat Hayam or האזינו—and
Ha'azinu you made that like normal text, פסולה—it's Pesula invalid. The גמרא
Gemara says: כי תניא ההיא בספר תורה. Ki tanya hahi b'sefer torah.
That's talking about a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. And if you think
about it, it's obviously talking about a ספר תורה Sefer Torah because
in a ספר תורה Sefer Torah you have a שירה. Shira. So
in a ספר תורה Sefer Torah it says if you write the
שירה Shira section—אז ישיר, Az Yashir, האזינו—if Ha'azinu you write that like
you write the normal text, right and left justified as a column,
it's invalid. And the normal text written like a שירה Shira is
invalid. So we're talking about a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. But for
some reason a מזוזה Mezuza does not have to follow a ספר
תורה Sefer Torah parameters and it could even be written, or maybe
it's nicer, of course we don't do that, but even be written
like a שירה. Shira. Okay. איתמר Itmar נמי Nami was said also:
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה אמר רב
אחא bar bar חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
מזוזה שעשאה שתים ושלש ואחת כשירה. Mezuza she'as'ah shtayim veshalosh ve'achat keshira.
If you make it two then three then one like we've been
talking about, that's kosher. ובלבד—but Uvilvad you're probably wondering why do we
do two, three, one? How about one, two, three? Three, two, one?
So now we're going to address that. שלא יעשנה כקובה. Shelo ya'asennah
kekuvah. You should not make it like a tent, which is basically
one, two, three, like a gradually expanding. Okay. ובלבד שלא יעשנה כזנב.
Uvilvad shelo ya'asennah kezanav. And don't make it like a tail, three,
two, one, narrowing. Somehow that is seen as, I don't know, as
less balanced, less symmetrical, less aesthetic. Again, maybe it's also just that
as the גמרא Gemara said, that the staggering of the three-two-one—of like
the short-long-short, you know, and continuing with
that. Short-long-short-long-short-long. That's a type of a structure that we are familiar
with in the שירה, Shira, in the, you know, האזינו, Ha'azinu, whereas
going just like a triangle or an inverted triangle is not a
structure that we ever see elsewhere. Okay. אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav
Chisda. Said Rav Chisda: על הארץ Al ha'aretz בשיטה אחרונה. Beshita achrona.
על הארץ Al ha'aretz you
can—you should have the words על הארץ Al ha'aretz on the last
line of the מזוזה. Mezuza. And that's what we do. איכא דאמרי
בסוף שיטה ואיכא דאמרי בתחלת שיטה. Ika de'amrei besof shita ve'ika de'amrei
betichlat shita. Some say you have it right-justified at the beginning—okay again
if you look there's a picture of—at some say,
actually the first one is בסוף שיטה, Besof shita, you have it
left-justified, the last two words on the line and white space before
it. ואיכא דאמרי בתחלת שיטה. Ve'ika de'amrei betichlat shita. And some say
you have it right-justified at the beginning. So if you take a
look in the שיטה מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzet, right, the left-justified is it
appears directly under the previous line so under the words כימי השמים
על הארץ Kimei hashamayim al ha'aretz and the right-justified is it appears
under the words at the beginning of the line לתת להם. Latet
lahem. כימי השמים על הארץ. ki'yemei hashamayim al ha'aretz. מאן דאמר בסוף
שיטה man d'amar b'sof shita if you say you put it left-justified,
כגבוה שמים על הארץ. k'govah shamayim al ha'aretz.
It's very nice visually, the שמים shamayim is directly over the earth,
okay? So that's very much a visual sort of signification of like
the days of the heaven above the earth, like and you know
the heaven is above the earth. ומאן דאמר בתחילה שיטה u'man d'amar
bit-chila shita if you say it's at the beginning of the line,
כי היכי דמרחקא שמים מארץ ki heichi d'merachka shamayim mei-aretz it's visual
in a different way, ארץ aretz is very distant from שמים shamayim
to symbolize that. Okay, so what we actually do for a מזוזה
mezuzah is that we actually do have על הארץ al ha'aretz on
the last line, it is right justified, we do not write it
like a שירה, shira, we actually write it like right and left
justified as I'm sure you're aware. There is an interesting question of
how you create the break between the two paragraphs of שמע Shema
and of the מזוזה mezuzah and we will discuss that tomorrow, we
will end here for now.